[Music]
hi all welcome back to another episode
of the asada pitch
i'm your host avery walker back from
maternity leave
and i'm joined today by usada's testing
and athlete services manager lindsey
stafford thanks for being here lindsay
yeah thanks avery for having me so
lindsay is on the front lines of our
effort to ensure that every u.s athlete
going to the tokyo games is competing
clean
and staying safe so she's going to help
answer some questions related to that
that have come up in recent weeks first
of all what does testing look like ahead
of the olympic and paralympic games this
year
yeah you know athletes should really
expect typical
out of competition in competition
testing leading into the games
one key change athletes may see is dry
blood spot testing or dbs
this is a new less invasive more athlete
friendly blood collection method
that usada is really encouraging the
global anti-open community to adopt more
broadly
um athletes should definitely expect to
see this collection method used more
frequently
by usada dope control officers of course
if athletes have questions about dbs
there's always more information on our
website and we always welcome your
direct outreach you know via phone or
email
awesome so it's testing different from
normal years
20 how was the plan impacted by cohen
yeah you know unfortunately i would say
it's definitely different from previous
years
covid has had a huge impact and
particularly on the you know competition
schedules for most sports
while events have been ramping back up
in the recent weeks
overall in competition testing is down
compared to pre-covered years simply due
to the reduction in events
um that said you know we are really
working closely with our science and
intel teams
our ngb partners and international
federations
to really maintain strategic testing
both in competition
and out of competition um to just ensure
we're sending a clean team usa
to tokyo again of course even with all
of these changes our number
one priority continues to be the safety
and well-being of our athletes
and our usada sample collection
personnel of course
is usada still practicing kova 19 safety
protocols
yes absolutely um all sample collection
personnel are still required to meet
usada's established coveted safety
protocols
this includes protective personal
protective equipment
regular kova testing of our sample
collection personnel
and modifications of certain sample
collection procedures
detailed information can again be found
on the website
but is also provided to the athlete
prior to sample collection
we want them to be informed and prepared
for how the process will be carried out
before it begins
and and you know of course we just want
to continue and we'll continue to
communicate with athletes
about what to expect from us as
vaccinations
hopefully enable us all to return um to
some sort of semblance of normalcy in
the coming weeks and months
yeah let's hope so athletes need to be
vaccinated to go to the gangs
no so vaccinations are not a requirement
to go to the games
um we do strongly encourage athletes and
or your
usada teams to get vaccinated um to just
maintain healthy and safe competition
yeah definitely are any of the kova 19
vaccines prohibited under the water
prohibited list
no so you know all vaccinations
authorized for use by the fda
are not prohibited under the water
prohibited list um
so you know athletes can really feel
confident um the current
cova vaccines do not contain any
prohibited substances so athletes can
feel free to go get vaccinated
and they don't even have to worry about
a positive test
awesome info thanks so much lindsay yeah
thank you for having me
well that's it for today but thanks for
watching and we back for another
episode soon